hello welcome to another video of cod
snippet so this video is again a
continuation of last video where we are
looking into spring data jpa so this is
basically the part three of it in the
first part we have seen the introduction
in the second part we have seen jpa
architecture and entity life cycle in
this video we are actually going to
write the code for it and we will
actually see the implementation how we
can Implement that so this is going to
be a fun video so sit back relax and
enjoy the show so let's quickly go
through the agenda again so here is
basically the agenda so in the first
part of it we have seen the introduction
in the introduction we have seen what is
jdbc what is omm what is jpa after that
we have seen the jpa architecture and
entity life cycle so architecture of jpa
we have seen entity life cycle we have
seen we have understood the internals of
jpa if you remember over here we have
seen this particular architecture of jpa
we have understood what is entity entity
manager entity manager Factory queries
transactions and persistence context
right and if you see over here we have
seen this entity life cycle as well
right you have seen all the stages
through which the entity will go through
right in its life cycle so if you
haven't watch this video just go ahead
and watch it it's basically the
prerequisite of this particular video
after that in this video we are going to
jump into the implementation part of it
right we will see how to set up a
project so we are going to uh create a
application management project basically
a job application management after that
we'll add some entities we'll see few
annotations which we need to add
entities after that
we will see three types of repositories
provided by jpa crude repository jpa and
paging and sorting repository after that
we will use some inbu methods in order
to perform some crude operations that we
will see what exactly is query methods
query annotations all of these things we
are going to look into this video right
that is basically about the agenda of
this particular video now let's jump to
the implementation right so let's first
set up the project right so in the last
video we have already saw that I have
created this particular project but how
to create that you just go to start.
spring.io here you can choose M here you
can choose this version which is by
default selected here you can add the
name of your application so I have added
uh application management system right
so you can add same over here or
whatever name you want to give you can
give after that here is a description
you can select jar from here Java 17 is
fine and you need to add a few
dependencies right so for example we are
going to add few rest API so we need
spring web right so spring web is
something which you can add that we are
going to use jpa so spring data jpa you
need to add after that we need a
database right so we will use some
inmemory database for now you can use
any database I'm using H2 over here
because it's easy to set up rate now
once you do that you just need to
generate a project from here and it will
download a zip file for you you need to
unzip and open it in intell J or
whatever editor you want right it will
have something like this uh so if you
see over here it will just have this
this application file right application
management system application
which will be annotated with at theate
Spring boot application these folders
are something which I have created so
controller basically there is nothing
inside controller repositories and
service but I have created one entity
which is applicant which we saw in the
last video right so for the example
purpose I have created this right but we
are going to modify it further it's just
a simple uh Java class right so what I'm
going to do over here I'm going to
create few controllers and service now
this boilerplate code I'm going to
create it and I'm going to explain as we
have created it multiple times in the
series so just in order to save time I
will just add few files in the
controller in the service and I will
highlight what exactly I have done all
right so I have added a couple of files
over here so if you see over here I have
added this controller applicant
controller right so basically first we
are going to implement functionality
specific to applicant right for example
a user who is going to apply for the job
right so here I have added two
controllers B basically first is a get
mapping to get all the applicants and
second is basically to save the
applicants right so basically a new
applicant which we want to save inside
of our database right that is basically
the overall controller I have added
simple stuff only I haven't added any
database or stuff yet I have just
created a boiler plate code right after
that we have created a service over here
in the service I have two functions
first is get applicant and and the
second one is basically to save
applicant rate so save applicant crude
rate so here I'm just taking applicant
as a input right and for now I'm just
returning null nothing specific your
applicant service should ideally talk to
your repository layer and store or get
the data right so that is the
implementation which is a Crux of this
video and we are going to actually
Implement that right first what we are
going to do let's first add a applicant
right so this is basically the entity
for the applicant so if you see over
here I go to this canvas over here so
first step basically is to create entity
when we want to create a jpa right this
is basically these are basically the
field that we are going to add inside
our database perhaps we can add one more
let's say we add status right so what is
the status of that particular
application that is something we can
also add right so all these fields we
have added now this is basically a
simple pojo class right very very simple
class this is not entity yet now in
order to convert this guy to entity we
need to make use of a annotation that is
called as entity right so we need to add
one annotation called as entity which
comes from persistence right so ad
theate entity I will add over here once
you add entity on top of this this guy
will be converted to entity right so
whenever we create object it will be
actually treated as a entity which will
be a table inside your database so you
need to just add this entity and just
forget right it will create a table with
this particular name inside a database
now every database needs a primary key
right every database needs a primary key
so let's say this long ID is going to be
a primary key for us so in order to
Define that you need to make use of
atate ID annotation right once you do
that this particular ID is going to be
the primary key now we have seen two
annotations over here entity and ID
right now whenever you create a new
applicant whenever you create a new
applicant are you going to manage this
ID on your own is user going to manage
it do user care about this ID right this
is something which is handled by our
system right user do not care about that
if I'm applying for job why do I care
about the ID that is going to saved in
the systems database right so I'm not
going to care so our system should
handle the autogeneration of this
particular ID right so that is when at
the rate generated value comes into
picture right so this is going to be a
generated value right now generated
value needs a strategy right what is a
strategy let's come back to it so there
are different type of strategies
basically so I'm selecting Auto over
here so this generated value takes one
argument that is basically a strategy
and this generation type is basically
enum which pass that particular value so
here if you see here we have multiple
generation types right so we have table
we have sequence identity uu ID Auto
right so we are making use of Auto now
right now each persistence provider have
its own way of creating this primary key
right for example hibernate will have
have its own way so basically if you
choose Auto then then your persistence
provider or let's say hibernate in this
case should pick up any one of these
right you just select auto and let the
other guy do whatever it wants to do
right the uid is basically a universally
unique identifier right so that will be
used for your primary key in this case
identity means it should use identity
column in order to provide the ID
sequence means it should use database
sequence in order to generate the
primary key and table means your
persistence provider must assign a
primary key for that particular entity
using a underl database table right it
says primary key for entity using an
underling database table to ensure
uniqueness right so that is basically
another generation type so this is
basically the generation type right so
let's come back over here so for now
what I'm doing I'm selecting Auto over
here now this is a minimum thing that
you need in order to use entities right
there are many other things that you can
use but these are the minimum things
right now what we are going to do let me
just create few getter sets quickly so
what I will do I'll go to generate and I
will create Getters and Setters for
everyone right so that will do that for
me so all the gets and sets are
generated right so that is basically our
entity so we have successfully created
The Entity for us right so that is
basically it about the entity let's go
back over here to controller now what
will happen over here this guy will just
return the list of applicant now first
what we need to do we need to save the
applicant right so in order in order to
do that we need to accept the request
body right so we will actually send the
Json when we call this particular rest
API post rest AP right so this will have
that detail that detail will be sent to
this function inside a service and now
the point come when we actually want to
Define our repository what we are going
to do over here is we are actually going
to save it to database at this stage and
get it from database at this stage right
so in order to do that we need a
repository now let's create a repository
right so as at this moment we are doing
just a crude operations right what I
will do I'll go to repositories create a
new Java class name it as applicant
crude repository we need to extend this
repository with crude repository right
there we go so basically we need to
extend this repository with crude
repository if we go back over here as we
have seen inside the agenda so if you
see we have three type of repositories
screw repository jpa repository and
paging and sorting repository right so
here we are implementing crude
repository and if you go back over here
to this diagram then if you can see over
here spring data jpa is kind of
abstraction layer on top of jpa right
internally spring data jpa is going to
use jpa only but what this guy is doing
this is simplifying stuff for us this is
providing us interfaces or layer of
abstraction to interact with jpa right
so when we create this class it should
not be class ideally it should be
interface because it's a abstract
because because it's abstraction right
so that's why we will create an
interface ideally right this interface
will extend this crude repository and
this scude repository will accept
parameters right so here we need to pass
parameters right so here first
parameters would be what will be the
entity right so our entity is basically
applicant and the second parameter is
what is the type of primary key of this
particular applicant so here if you go
inside it our primary key ID is
basically this ID and what is the type
of that long type so what we will do we
will just go back and add long over
here right now that's it basically so
that is the only thing you need to do in
order to create applicant crude
repository right very very easy stuff
right you don't even need to implement
any methods you don't need to write any
code in order to do DB operations that
how easy your spring data jpa is right
once you do that what you need to do is
you need to go inside your service and
create the object of application crude
repository right so let me just import
it what I will do I will
just create a private
variable what I will do I'll just use a
field injection for now so what I'll do
auto right this is basically the
dependency injection I'm talking about
if you're not sure what is the
dependency injection then then I have
already created a video on dependency
injection in the same playlist you can
go ahead and check that so now we have
this grud repository created already
right now what we are going to do over
here
now what we will do over here we need to
save this applicant right now so what we
will do we'll just say applicant crude
repository dot save and what save method
will take save method will take what
applicant you want to save right and
that is it now this statement should
save it inside your database right now
what we will do we'll just return that
from here itself and remove the
statement because save will return the
same entity applicant and applicant will
be sent back to your controller right
and we can use this applicant crude
repository here as well so what we will
do here applicant crude repository. find
we will do find all because we want
everyone right because we want the list
of it now here if you see this find all
method is returning iterable right but
if we want to return list rate so we
need to convert this all to list rate so
for that purpose what I'm doing over
here is I'm just creating a new AR list
and I will just add each element to that
particular AR list by using a loop right
so very very simple stuff over here we
can use streams as well but let's keep
things simple over here right what I
will do I will just return applicant
list from
here so that should return the list of
applicants right back to our controller
right so that is basically it right
apart from that if you go here inside
resources then we have a few
configurations added related to H2
database so here we have added URL we
have added this driver class we have
added some us username and password we
have added this to enable the console so
that we will be able to see the database
on the console right after that we have
added hibernate ddl auto update so that
hibernate will be able to perform update
operations and we have added JPS show
SQL so that we can see what SQL it is
creating right in the console log output
right so that is basically the
configuration now I think we are at this
stage when we can run this application
right so what I will do I will just go
to this particular class and I will hit
run from here here let's see what
happens there we go it seems that our
application has started so if you see
over here started application management
system application in this much seconds
right so now what we can do before doing
any operations let's just go to a
browser and let me just open this
particular console so if you see over
here we have H2 console enabled at this
particular path so what I will do I will
just load this URL and it should show
something like this right this is
basically the H2 console right so what I
will do I'll just maximize it or
increase the size of it so that it is
clearly visible right so now here you
need to add driver class jdbc URL and
stuff right so driver is basically the
same because we are using H2 but here
the jdbc URL would be different because
the name of our DB here is different
right so that is something which you
will find over here in the same log you
just need to copy it from here go back
to your browser and just paste it and
what username and password we added
while we add configuration let's go back
and check so essay and password right
what I will do here I will add sa and
here I will add password right and I
will say connect so that should connect
it right so that is basically how the
console of H2 looks right we have seen
this multiple times in the series if you
are following the series you might be
aware of this already now here if you
see we have this table we have we have
this applicant table we have this ID
field email
name phone status everything we have
right did we write any code to create
this first of all no we did not who is
creating it who is creating it jpa is
creating it right so if you go back over
here in the architecture then here this
entity is basically managed by this
entity manager then some provider like
hibernate would have created a query and
HIIT this query to create a DB table
inside this database now let's see if we
can check something like that in the
logs right now if you could see this
here it is making use of hibernate right
so it is actually writing a hibernate
query if you see over here this is a
hibernate query create table applicant
and it is defining all the variables
that we have inside our entity right it
is defining a primary key as well right
everything it is doing for us it is also
doing sequence generation and everything
right so it is taking care of everything
from the database side we don't need to
do anything from our side right so here
in this case the provider is hibernate
the spring data jpa is internally using
jpa and jpa is internally using hypernet
as a provider to perform this database
operations now now probably you'll be
able to link that this entity is managed
by entity manager and this particular
transaction and query is created by
hibernate and that guy is creating your
database right now when we debug we will
actually see how your entity manager
looks like but for now we have this
particular table created with us and our
application is up and running right what
we can do we can try to add a few
applicants now right now let me just
quickly create this particular API
inside Postman if you see over here I
have added this particular URL right so
URL and API SL applicants I have added
over here so if you see over here we
have that in request mapping over here
API SL applicant and first we will add
so we need post mapping right in order
to add it so what I will do I'll select
post from here let's provide all these
details that we have added from here
right so if you see our entity then we
have name email phone status right then
let's let's add this data so basically
let's go name as pushpa and uh we have
this email ID over here and we have some
phone number and status is let's say
active I don't know why pushpa is
applying for job but let's say he needs
a job pushpa means our pushparaj right
which is becoming famous day by day so
let's add him right now let me just hit
this real quick if you see we have got
some response that that means pushparaj
applicant is added right now let's add
one more so what is the other character
from pushpa right so let's add K right K
again K is again another character let's
add but as far as I remember that guy is
dead right in the part one but let it be
that guy might need a job in hell so if
I add it as you can see uh the id2 again
is added over here so this ID we are not
passing over here right so if you see
carefully this ID is something which we
are not passing from here so that is
something which is generated
automatically as we have seen we have
added generation type over here right
gener value generation type as Auto
right so that is basically it is
creating automatically for us so now at
this stage if we go to our database let
me just reload this guide real quick and
we need to connect it again I believe if
you see over here this applicant right
so what I will do I'll just add some
query like
select star from applicant right select
right so let me just run this real quick
so if you see over here we have our
pushparaj we have our Ki and both of
these guys are added inside our database
with status as active right so super
that means things are working out for us
our jpa is working fine right now we
have added one more API rate what API we
have added so if you go to controller we
have added this get all applicants which
will get the list of applicants for us
from our service and it will use crude
repository to find everything and it
will just return the list let's go back
over here and let's try to hit the get
API of it right so if I hit the get API
in this case it it is not going to use
this Json data if I send it it will just
return as the list so if you see over
here pushparaj and qudi are returned
over here in the list that is basically
read operations we have create and read
we have already seen right that is
working fine for us now if we go back
over here then do you see this queries
over here if you see over here we have
this insert into applicant which is
inserting data for us after that we
added one more we added KD after that we
hit a select command which is basically
selecting stuff for us right now what we
will do let's run this application in
debug mode actually and let's see what
happens so uh let me just start it in
debug mode I'll do from here I can start
in debug mode stop and rerun so the
application is started now let's go
ahead and add one more applicant over
here right before that what I'm going to
do is I am going to add a few debug
points so here in the controller I will
add one no need to add it in controller
basically let's go to service and add
basically right so here in the service I
will add one here and we will actually
go inside save and we will see what
exactly is happening if you see over
here we have this save method inside
crude repository interface and and if
you go inside the implementation of it
then this is again provided by a jpa
itself right if you see over here if you
see over here we have this entity
manager object right so this is
basically the entity manager object
right so I've added a debug point over
there if you remember in the last video
we have gone through JP architecture
right so entity is basically managed by
your entity manager so it's the same
entity manager we are talking about here
in this implementation right so let's
see what happens in this case right so
let's add one more applicant over here
this time let's say we will add shali
right so let's add shali what is the
surname of shiv who knows we are going
to add this so let me just hit send it
should wait for a in the debug mode so
we have added this debug point over here
right now if I
proceed then it will show The Entity
manager so if you see over here we have
this entity manager object if you go to
here and try to check the definition of
it then you will be able to see that
it's entity manager shared entity
manager proxy for Target Factory right
just click on view so you'll be able to
see that it's object of local container
entity manager Factory Bean right so
this is basically spring internals right
we don't need to go inside that is
basically that this en manager is being
created for us and if you see we have
this persistence provider which is
basically hibernate right in this case
do you see over here that it's a
hibernate right so here basically it is
going to purist the object as it is a
new object right so it is internally
using entity manager. persist now when
we move forward right move forward from
here the entity should actually be added
inside our database right so if you go
back over here let me just refresh this
real quick quick and let me just log in
again if you see over here in the
applicant we will just run it so you see
that there is one object now few people
may have doubt that where is the other
two we have added push p and K right as
we have redun our application the data
is basically vanished because H2 is in
memory database and it will be reloaded
each time you reload your application or
restart your application right so if you
want the data to persist use something
like MySQL which will pers assist your
data right or keep the data inside your
database so that is basically how you
can add the data and get the data by
using JP in the similar way you have
multiple functions so if I go inside any
service and show you the functions right
so let me just show you a real quick so
let's say applicant cude repository dot
then you will see that you will have
save you have find all count delete
delete all delete all by ID right so
this is basically delete stuff you have
save all find by ID right you have many
functions over here which you can make
use of from crude repository so these
functions are measuredly for create get
delete and update operations right so
that is basically crude repository for
you and that is how you can implement it
right now as we have seen in the agenda
so let me just go back over there in the
agenda as we have seen there are more
types of repositories so crude
repositories is something which we have
already seen after that we have paging
and sorting repository and after that we
have jpa repository right so we have two
more repositories to look into we have
seen crude repository we have seen that
it performs crude operation now what is
different in these and this repository
right so first let's see the difference
between all three and then what we will
do we will just Implement and see
examples of paging and sorting and JP
repositories right right so if we go
over here then this is basically how we
can visualize it right so basically
first we have crude repository that we
have seen this Repository over here
provides a very basic crude operations
like create read update and delete kind
of stuff right very easy stuff and this
repository is basically very lightweight
and suitable for your simple operations
right you can go ahead and use this when
you need to perform very very simple
operations inside your application right
then comes paging and sorting repository
right so as the name suggest this
repository will give you some features
related to paging and sorting right so
what this repository will do this will
extend your crude repository that means
this guy will have all the functions of
your crude repository plus few more
functions related to paging and sorting
right so we will look into that when we
actually see the examples of it after
that we have a jpa repository right so
this comes from Spring data jpa right
now this jpa repository extends paging
and sorting repository that means this
will include the functions from both
crude repository and paging and sorting
Repository along with few jpa specific
functions for example we have flush
method right in order to flush the data
inside database right so after that we
have methods as save and flush delete in
batch after that this also supports
something called as query methods which
is again a very very important feature
so that is something we are going to
look into as well right so that is
basically how the crude repository
paging and sorting repository and and
jpa repository are related and different
from each other right now if I go back
to document then if you see over here
then we have these features and for each
feature we will see what crude
repository will provide what paging and
sorting and what jpa will provide right
so if we talk about basic crude
operations then crude repository will be
able to provide that as paging and
sorting is extending crude repository so
that guy also will able to provide basic
crude operation and and so do jpa
repository right so all three
repositories will provide basic crude
operations right after something called
as pagination comes into picture then
this guy won't be able to do it crude
repository right because this guy will
do only basic stuff so pagination will
be provided by paging and sorting
repository and jpa repository after that
sorting same thing right this guy won't
be able to do it but both of these two
will be able to do it right then we have
JPS specific methods for example flush
then both crude and paging and sorting
will not be able to do only jpa will be
able to do right and we have custom
query methods and batch operations which
will be only supported by your jpa
repository right so this is how we can
visualize it how jpa repository is
different from these two and what
exactly is difference between these
three right so this is basically a
famous interview question as well people
ask what are three type of repositories
and what is the difference between them
right so you know what to answer now
right now as we have seen the
differences between them and we have
also seen the example of crude
repository let's go and Implement paging
and sorting repository now right so in
the same way as we have created
application cude repository let's create
a new interface again and add this
application pag and sorting repository
so that should do it for us now what we
will do we will extend with what which
one now paging and sorting repository
right and we again we will add here our
entity which is basically applicant
right applicant and the primary key is
long right so that should do the job for
us right now let's create the object of
this guy let's inject it inside our
applicant service right so what I will
do I will just create object of it
application paging and sorting
repository and I will just simply
autowire it right so for now I'm Auto
wiring it but the best practice of
dependency injection is basically doing
a Constructor injection right so again
dependency injection is something you
can check in the other video where I
have covered it in details right now
what we will do over here we will
Implement a function we will Implement a
function to get application with
pagination right so here what we are
going to do is we are going to implement
this function get applicants with
pagination right now we want to pag in
edit we want to say what exactly the
size of page that we want over here
right so what we are going to do over
here is I will just say applicant paging
and sorting repository dot find all
right find all and we will need to
create the object of page request over
here page request
of page and and basically page size and
the size of elements on each page right
so that is basically how we can
Implement paging right so what we are
going to do over here so we have
implemented this function now let's
quickly add a API for it over here so
this should basically do it right so
I've just added a new API over here what
it will do it will just call the service
and say get application and it will call
our service function with this page and
with this size right so page and size I
have taken from user by using request
parameter right so what we can do over
here let me just rerun this application
right and let's try to run it quickly so
it failed so there is some error
basically we are not returning this we
should actually return this right so
should not fail anymore looks like there
is extra bracket as well so let me just
try to run it now should work ideally
yeah it is working now so what I will do
I will just go to our Postman and I will
try to call our new API saying page
right so here we need need two request
parameters now first is Page let's say
want one one page over here and size
let's say we have we want two right so
if we send this request now right it
should not be post it should be get
ideally so if I send this request now
and if you can see over here so if you
see the output over here we have this
content right and the content is empty
now because we don't have much data
inside our application and it is again
giving the object of pageable that is
the whatever the page size we want and
what is the page number we want right
now let's first before hitting this API
let's do one thing let's try to add some
data inside our application so what I
will do I'll just create a duplicate API
over here what I will do I'll just add
the same body over here in Json format
and I will post it right let's see so
the data should be added let's add some
more data let's add
pushpa right so pushpa is also added
let's add our other guy what was it K
right K Rd also added there we go let's
add one more let's add K's brother
basically right so that also is added
let's come back to our page API right so
here we have used paging and sorting so
now if I request so if you see over here
we are getting entries three and four
when we say page number one and size as
two right so on page number one we have
two entries right H ready and Je ready
is coming over here right but basic
basically page size start from zero
right so if I add zero over here let me
add zero and send it so our first two
entries will be here right this is
basically pagination that we are
implementing so on first page we have
these two right on second page that is
page number one we have these two
entries right if I increase the size to
let's say three right then on the first
page you will only have one entry right
but on the Zero page we will have three
entries because is now three right so as
you can see we have three entries over
here 1 2 and three right basically that
is how pagination is working right so on
each page how much data we want that is
something we are defining over here
right so if I pass four then it will
show all the entries on single page only
and when I pass first page now it should
be empty in this case right so that is
basically how the pagination works and
all these thing is easily achievable by
using paging and sorting repository that
we are looking over here that is
basically how you can implement it very
very simple right right so that is
basically how we can Implement paging
and sorting repository right now let's
jump to a very very important point over
here right so now we have seen crude
repository and paging and sorting
repository and its implementation right
but let's come back over here so this
behavior that we are looking that the
one which I have just highlighted that
that crude repository extends paging and
sorting repository and that guy extends
jpa repository is Val valid for older
version of spring data so at this moment
also if you go and Google this
relationship between these two or the
difference between these three you will
find that crude repository extends
paging and sorting repository and that
guy extends jpa repository right but
this behavior is not valid in the recent
version of spring data right now there
are few modifications and new
introductions in the new version of
spring data so what are those let's see
so if you see over here in the new
version of spring data they are
addressing a major issue that we also
have faced over here so if you remember
while doing a get operation from crude
repository when we did find all it
returned us the itable right but that is
not something which we want we want the
list right we want this list what we had
to do we had to convert that itable to a
list and then return right so this is a
problem right this is basically the
problem they are trying to address so
what they have done they have introduced
new repositories like list crude
repository and list paging and sorting
repository right
so if you go back over here then the new
implementation would look something like
this right if you see over here this is
how it would look like so at the top you
will have a repository so this is
basically the marker interface this you
will have here as well right here also
you will have that right so just a
marker interface it will not have any
methods right so at the top you will
have repository so if you go back over
here and try to see this rude repository
and just go inside it then you will see
that that it is extending a repository
and which is kind of a marker interface
that we have without any methods right
so that is basically your repository at
the top then crude repository will
extend repository and paging and sorting
repository will again extend repository
now major point to notice over here is
that your paging and sorting repository
is not extending crude repository in
this case right so the behavior that we
saw over here that crude repository was
extending paging and sorting reposit
is not valid anymore right here paging
and sorting repository does not extend
crude repository right here they have
introduced two new things right list
crude repository and list paging and
sorting repository right and our jpa guy
will now extend both of these list crude
repository and list paging and sorting
repository because it needs method from
both crude repository and paging and
sorting repository so it had to extend
both of these right so that it can
incorporate all the methods that are
provided by all these right so that is
basically the difference in the new
version and and a major difference right
so basically first we have seen the
older version with this problem and this
problem is now solved with something
called as list crude repositories right
so if I go here and instead of using
crude repository if I use list crude
repository Now list crude repository
then what will happen here what we can
do instead of accepting atable we can
just accept the list of applicants and
just remove everything right so the
overhead of converting that itable is
now removed what we can do over here we
can directly just return it from here
now all these codes is just came down to
a single line because of this new
repository right so if you go to find
all now you will see that it is
returning list and find all by ID is
also returning a list and this is
basically list crude repository which is
extending crude repository as we have
seen in this particular diagram right so
that is basically how it looks now and
if you see paging and sorting repository
now over here if I go inside paging and
sorting repository then you will see
that it is not extending crude
repository rather it is extending
repository which is kind of a marker
interface right and if I Implement list
paging and sorting over here then let's
see what happens so let me just quickly
import it and let's go inside it we have
only one method which is related to sort
right it is not related to paging right
so if you're using sort then you can
directly accept list right but if you
are using paging then you will need to
take itable only as we are taking it
over here right that is basically it and
why they need to do it so if I show you
real quick then we have the spring data
Commons release notes over here so we
have the spring data release notes right
so if you see over here then they are
implementing something called as list
crude repositories and they say that
sorting repositories no longer inherit
from crude repositories right loud and
clear you can also see that over here
that paging and sorting repository no
longer extends screw root repository
right if in case we need to achieve the
same behavior then we must not only
extend sorting repository but also
extend crude repository explicitly right
that means what they are trying to say
over here is if you want the same
behavior then go ahead and extends one
more repository over here which is crude
repository of applicant
and law right so like that we need to do
after that so if we do something like
that over here then we can use our
paging and sorting repository to perform
crude operations as well for example
let's say applicant paging and sorting
repository do save now it will have save
methods right so that is how you need to
achieve it if you want to achieve the
older Behavior right so the link of this
release notes I will add in the
description you can go ahead and check
this right so if I come back over here
this is basically the new hierarchy and
that is basically the major difference
now between paging and sorting reposit
so this Behavior also will be changed
over here because paging and sorting
repository do not really support crude
operations anymore right so this block
will be changed over here so here it was
supporting but here it will not support
it will just support pagination and
sorting right nothing else right so
that's about our two repositories crude
repository plus we have seen list crude
repositories as well so I will just
update this and add list crude
repository as well over here so what I
will do I'll just paste this and say
list grud repository same with list
paging and sorting repository right the
only thing remaining now is jpa
repository and very very important
aspect now right so let's see let's
Implement that now now let's go to our
application and let's uh add a new
interface basically saying applicant jpa
repository now right and it will just
extend jpa
repository jpa repository right and here
again we will say our applicant and long
which is the primary key of our
applicant right and that's it again now
let's make use of it in our service
right so what I will do I will just
inject that as well explicitly over here
I'll say so I will say
private applicant jpa
repository applicant jpa repository and
I will simply to it right so it's
basically injected right now here if I
go inside jpa Repository then then
you'll be able to see that it is
extending list crude repository along
with list paging and sorting repository
right so that is basically what we have
seen over here in this diagram right so
it is basically extending both of them
right and this guy was already
supporting find all right so if you so
if in case you would have used jpa
repository over here then this problem
that we have seen with crude repository
was already solved in jpa repository
right so jpa guy is already clever right
so that that is basically jpa repository
and if you see over here we have these
methods like flush save and flush save
all and flush and we have and we have
few batch specific method delete all in
batch delete all in batch delete all by
ID in batch and delete all in batch so
apart from these methods of jpa right it
will provide few few other things as
well right so this is common right this
is very easy you can simply implement it
right but the point of highlight when we
use jpa is your query methods right
query methods now what is query methods
now let's say over here we have this
applicant right now in this applicant
let's say I want to find applicant by
using status right let's say I only want
applicants which are active right which
are active or we can say I also want to
check the list of inactive applicants
over here right so what I need to do
traditionally is I need to write a query
for that right because over here if I do
applicant JP repository do
find by
status then I don't see any method like
that right find by ID might be there but
find by status is not there right that
is when query methods comes into picture
right query method is something which
comes in handy in such cases right so in
that case what you need to do is you
just need to create a function let's say
find let's say find by status I want to
find this particular applicant by status
right and if I just add that and let
let's say I will just pass a string
status over here
right and I will Define a return type
right so I will say I want the list of
applicants
right and that's it now I have added
this method so basically based on this
naming convention that I want to find by
status right it what it will do it will
explicitly create a query and jpa will
return us the output right I want to
find by status that means it is pretty
clear that I want to find this applicant
by status right and status is one of the
field inside our applicant right so it
will automatically create a query at its
end and I don't really need to add that
particular query right so that is how
this guy works right let's say if I want
to find by name and status as well right
so I can simply modify that saying by
name and by status and that's it and
here I will just pass name as well now
how simple is that right how simple is
that now let's quickly see the example
of one right so what I will do I will
just use this function somewhere so
let's go to our service and what we can
do we can just create another get
function so what I will do I will just
add it over here get applicant I will
say
get applicant by status right and we'll
just take a string status from user and
what we can do now we can make use of
jpa repository so what I do applicant
jpa repository do find by status and I
will just simply pass this status and
that's it now let's quickly add endpoint
to check that so what I will do I'll
just add another get endpoint right
another get end point I will add and I
will add kind of a mapping over here we
add mapping as get by status right this
also I will modify get applicant by
status after that I will just call get
application by status and we will need a
request parameter as status so I will
just add that request parameter over
here which will be a
string and it will be a
status right and same status we will
pass over
here right that's it now let me just
quickly rerun this application let's see
what happens right so let me just rerun
it let it come up it is started what I
will do first I will add some data in
inside our application so I will add
this guy Jolly R is active right let's
add K as inactive because that guy is
dead right so I will send it with the
status as inactive and let's say our
pushparaj is active right and let's add
one more perhaps so our shali also is
active right pushparaj and shali are
basically very active so uh I have added
all these four so if I go back over here
or let me perhaps just create a a new
API over here and Perms I will add
status and I want active status right
and now if I send it oh I need to change
the url as well I will add what what we
have added over here get by state right
so let me just copy that and let me add
it over here and let's send it so do you
see over here so jolly pushpa and shali
these the these guys are active right
and if you want to see who are inactive
then I can just change the status over
here and let's send it again if you see
over here then K is basically inactive
right so that's how basically your named
methods will work right and this guy
also support sorting right okay so let
me tell you that as well if I go over
here go back to jpa repository then I
can also add something like sorting in
what order I want to
sort it right so for example for example
I want to sort these guys right so what
I'll do I'll use order by Clause right
we use order by clause in school right
so I'll say order by name order by name
that means name of these guys name of
our guys and what order I should give I
let let me give ascending right let me
give ascending at the moment so if I go
let me just rerun this same application
right I need to call the new method now
now right so let me just rerun again and
again we need to add few folks right
because our application has been
reloaded so now if I hit this particular
API again let's see what happens so if
you see over here then it is sorted
based on names we have Jolly first then
pushpa then shali right and if I pass
inactive status over here then let's see
what happens as you can see B Singh come
first and k comes second right that is
basically name based sorting that we are
achieving over over here right so that
is how we can make use of query methods
right that is basically query methods
that we have over here so lastly let's
see query annotations so here we can use
at theate query annotations as well
right so let's say there is some use
case that we have observed which cannot
be fulfilled by query methods right for
example let's go back over here and
let's try to implement functionality
like like find application by partial
name right so let's say we have K Redd
I'm just passing Redd over here but if I
say find by name then it will try to
match the exact name right so here in
this case this will not work right this
is not a query method format that we
have in that case what we can do we can
actually write a query on top of this
guy right so here you can actually write
SQL query right so how that query would
look like it would look like something
like this right let me just add it over
here so select a from applicant where a
do name like and what is this name this
name will be replaced by this name right
and in order to replace that we need to
add something called as param here we
need to Define that this is my param is
going to be the key of that param is
basically the name right this is
basically it is going to be right so
let's quickly Implement a API by using
this method right so what I will do I'll
go to service I will add another get API
over here I'll say partial name I'll
accept name inside string I will make
use of the other method now
find by applicant's partial name and I
will just pass name over here right I'll
return it right now in the controller
let's add another API by name right and
here what I will do I will say get
applicant
by partial name and here in the request
parameter let's let's accept
name and here let's say get by partial
name and let's pass name to this guy
right that should do it it let me just
rerun this application let's see what
happens
now and I will go back over here add few
folks so let me just add b
space sing now right so sing spelling
should be i n g right so now I will just
add this guy and I will just quickly
duplicate this tab what I will do I will
just modify this API according to this
so we have get by name over here and
what we need we need name in this case
right so here instead of status we need
name right so here what we'll do we'll
just say sing right now as you can see
we have we have got b sing right so that
is basically how you can use at theate
query
annotation right so this also we have
seen right so there are lot many things
we have seen in this video and we have
seen all type of repositories over here
as well right so I will push this
project on a GitHub repository and I
will add the link in the description you
can just clone and start playing around
with this particular project right so
that marks the end of this particular
video and that is basically spring data
jpa for you right it's very very easy
framework and and anyone can just go
ahead and start using it right very very
easy you just need to understand few
fundamental concepts that we have
understood in this video and last two
videos right if you like the video hit
the like button don't forget to
subscribe to code snippet share this
video with your friends so that they are
also aware of spring data jpa and the
new version of spring data jpa right
that is very very important that's it
for this video see you in the next video